Guide to the United Federation of Teachers Photographs PHOTOS 019
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
United Federation of Teachers Photographs
1928-1987, (Bulk 1970s)
1970-1979
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
United Federation of Teachers
PHOTOS 019
29 Linear Feet (29 boxes)
The United Federation of Teachers (American Federation of Teachers, Local 2) represents public school teachers and associated personnel in New York City. The Collection consists of 33,500 black and white photographs that span the years 1928 to 1987, but are concentrated in the 1970s, documenting the UFT and its activities, chapters and members, and New York City schools and students. Also well-represented are images of the activities and member organizations of New York State United Teachers, as well as New York schools and students outside of New York City. A small, but significant number of images concern two predecessor unions, the Teachers' Union of the City of New York and the Teachers' Guild. NOTE: This collection is housed offsite and advance notice is required for use.
circa 38,800 black and white 8" x 10" photographs, 200 35mm black and white negatives, 100 color slides.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Photographs from the files of the New York Teacher were donated to the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives by the United Federation of Teachers in 1987. The union made additional donations of photographs in later years, including, in 1992, photographs concerning the Teachers' Union (a predecessor of the UFT) collected by Mildred Grossman, a younger member of the Workers' Film and Photo League and a blacklisted New York City teacher. The photographs in this latter donation were shot by a number of different photographers, including Grossman herself. The accession numbers associated with this collection are 1987.003, NPA.2003.038, NPA.2004.087.
Arrangement
Series I is divided into organizational and topical subseries, arranged alphabetically by district, local, or chapter names, except where otherwise noted; series II is arranged alphabetically; series III is arranged chronologically within three subseries.
The materials are grouped into 3 series:
Missing Title
I. New York Teacher Photograph Files, 1951-1987.
II. United Federation of Teachers General Photograph Files, 1960s-1980s.
III. Predecessor Unions, 1928-1961.
Historical/Biographical Note
The United Federation of Teachers (UFT) was formed in March 1960. The UFT immediately began its campaign to gain collective bargaining rights and won a promise from the New York City School Board of a collective bargaining election in the 1960-1961 school year. When the Board failed to honor its pledge, a one-day work stoppage and broad support from other unions forced the issue. The election, in which the National Education Association (NEA) and the Teachers' Union stood in opposition to the UFT, was held in December 1961; the UFT won. Teachers swelled the ranks of the new union, and soon specialized chapters were created to accommodate other categories of school employees (for example, laboratory technicians, school secretaries, psychologists, guidance counselors, and para-professionals) who became part of the UFT. When UFT's president, Charles Cogen, was elected president of the American Federation of Teachers (AFT), in 1964, he was succeeded by Albert Shanker, who served as president of the UFT from 1964 until 1986. Albert Shanker's tenure coincided with some of the most challenging times for New York City schools, in an era characterized by rapidly changing demographics, racial conflict, demands from parents and community-based groups, overcrowded and dilapidated buildings, teacher shortages and citywide fiscal crises.
By the mid-1960s the UFT had more than 50,000 members and was the largest local union in the AFL-CIO. The union responded to changing conditions in the schools by backing the More Effective Schools program, aimed at improving teaching methods in underachieving schools, and other innovative programs. But by September 1967, when contract negotiations with the Board of Education broke down, the teachers were driven to strike to achieve an increase in wages and benefits. In the wake of the strike the union was fined and Shanker sentenced to fifteen days in prison for violation of the state's Taylor Law, banning strikes by public employees. Earlier in the year the city had agreed to implement a school decentralization plan in exchange for increased state funding. The plan, which created three experimental school districts in East Harlem, the Lower East Side of Manhattan and Ocean Hill-Brownsville in Brooklyn, was greeted with enthusiasm by African-American and Latino parents who hoped for a greater voice in their children's education. The UFT, on the other hand, feared that community control of schools would undermine teachers' hard-won rights and weaken the union's bargaining power. Bitter conflict ensued, resulting first in a walk-out of 350 teachers in Ocean Hill-Brownsville and, in September 1968, a citywide teachers strike. Albert Shanker was again sentenced to jail for leading the strike. An uneasy settlement, involving a state-appointed trustee in Ocean Hill-Brownsville and reinstatement of displaced teachers, left a legacy of distrust between the union and some community activists and scarred race relations in the city for many years.
In 1972 Shanker was a central figure in negotiating the merger of the AFT and the National Education Association (NEA) in New York State. The resulting organization, New York State United Teachers, brought more than 100,000 upstate teachers into the labor movement and was a rare example of close and amicable cooperation between the two major national organizations representing teachers. In 1974 Shanker was elected president of the American Federation of Teachers. Retaining his position as UFT president for some years, he went on to play a key role in re-establishing the city's fiscal stability after the fiscal crisis of the mid-1970s. He was succeeded as president of the UFT by Sandra Feldman in 1986, and died after a long struggle with cancer in 1997.
The UFT had its origins in the Teachers' Union (TU) of New York City, and the Teachers' Guild. The Teachers' Union was organized in 1916 and chartered as Local 5 of the American Federation of Teachers (AFT). A growing political struggle within its ranks between a left wing dominated by Communist Party members and their sympathizers, and a more moderate group consisting of socialists, liberals and less ideologically inclined teachers resulted in a split in 1935, when its president, a moderate, withdrew with a majority of the membership to found the Teachers Guild. In 1941 the AFT revoked the Teachers' Union's charter. Over a number of years the TU was weakened by McCarthy-era persecution and the increasingly successful organizing efforts of the rival Teachers Guild (and later the United Federation of Teachers). It went out of existence in 1964.
The Teachers Guild, born in 1941, when it won recognition by the American Federation of Teachers, addressed the problems of a fragmented workforce, divided into small teachers' organizations representing a multitude of ethnic and religious groups, geographical areas and distinct school levels (elementary, junior high school and high school), and began the long struggle for collective bargaining rights in the New York City school system. A job action initiated by militant leaders of the High School Teachers Association (HSTA) in 1959, gave the Guild an opportunity to demonstrate its commitment to building solidarity among all categories of teachers. David Selden, then the Guild's only full-time organizer (and later president of the American Federation of Teachers), enlisted the help of younger Guild Board members such as junior high-school teachers George Altomare and Albert Shanker. After month-long picket lines at schools across the city, substantial gains were won by the high-school teachers, and bridges had been built which would eventually lead toward merger between the Guild and the HSTA. That merger was effected in March 1960, with Guild president Charles Cogen taking over as president of the newly-formed United Federation of Teachers.
Related Material at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
United Federation of Teachers Oral History Collection. (Oral History #9)
United Federation of Teachers Photographs, Part II, Hans Weissenstein Negatives.
United Federation of Teachers Records (Wagner #22)
Scope and Content Note
The United Federation of Teachers Photographs Collection is comprised of ca. 38,800 black and white (mostly 8x10) prints and a small number of negatives. Most of these come from the photograph files of the New York Teacher, the newspaper of New York State United Teachers (NYSUT), and most date from the 1970s and 1980s. The largest single portion of the Collection is devoted to individual officers and members of the UFT and of NYSUT-particularly Albert Shanker, UFT president from 1964 to 1986. Also documented are the activities and meetings of UFT chapters (including those for non-teacher school employees), NYSUT affiliates and teacher associations; schools, students, and teachers (particularly in New York City); dinners, luncheons, award ceremonies, scholarship presentations, dedications, memorial services, and check presentations, as well as holidays and other "dedicated days" and weeks that mark the regular rhythm of organizational life and punctuate the school year. The collection also contains images depicting professional development via training and workshops, the American Federation of Teachers, other teacher unions, and the UFT/NYSUT's relationship to New York City and state politics and politicians. In addition, a small but significant portion of the collection reflects New York City's fiscal crisis of the 1970s and the rising consciousness of ethnic identity among students, teachers, and parents, as well as related episodes of conflict in the New York City school system, such as the Ocean Hill-Brownsville crisis.
NOTE: This collection is housed offsite and advance notice is required for use.
The collection also offers some visual documentation for two of the UFT's predecessor unions, the Teachers' Union and the Teachers' Guild.
While images shot by many different photographers may be seen throughout the collection, the work of Hans Weissenstein (aka Whitestone Studios), Sam Reiss, and Dan Miller is particularly well-represented.
The basic unit of the collection, as described in the Container List, is a "shoot"-e.g., a photograph or a group of photographs shot by one or more photographers of one event, usually, but not always, on the same day. The container list represents a complete list of these shoots, arranged into subseries and sub-subseries, which are arranged chronologically (with undated shoots following dated materials), unless otherwise noted. Each entry includes a date (usually of the event, but occasionally of the issue in which the image was published), if known, and a shoot description derived from the original caption information. The same shoot may be (and often is) shown in two different subseries when its subject content falls into more than one category.
The Collection is divided into three series:
Series I: New York Teacher Photograph Files, 1951-1987, is comprised of photograph files from the New York Teacher, NYSUT's official newspaper, established in September 1972, and published in co-terminous New York City and New York State editions. The New York City edition was published for UFT members, the New York State edition for NYSUT teacher associations and locals. The two editions appear to have been closely allied, sharing office space as well as some staff and resources (presumably including photographs). While the majority of the images focus on the UFT and New York City schools, there are also a large number of images relating to NYSUT and upstate New York teacher associations that reflect this close association. The series spans the period from 1951 to 1987, with most dated photographs coming from the 1970s and early 1980s. (More than one-third of the images are undated, but most appear to have been shot in the 1970s and 1980s.) Photographs that pre-date the creation of the New York Teacher may have come from the files of the UFT's earlier, pre-NYSUT publication, United Teacher, and before that, the files of New York Teacher News, published by the Teachers' Union.
Series I is divided into 21 subseries:
Note to the Researcher: Each photograph in Series I (New York Teacher Photograph Files), has an original "unit number" written on the back, and each entry in the container list for Series I also includes a unit number, in the column headed "Item." More than one photograph may have the same unit number. For the Box and Folder location for a given "unit number" go to: http://www.nyu.edu/library/bobst/research/tam/np19_pt_1.pdf. Within the folder, look at the backs of the prints to find the photograph(s) with the unit number matching the one in the description. Photographs with different unit numbers may share a folder, so it is necessary to consult the unit numbers in order to identify the prints matching the description.
Subseries I:A: United Federation of Teachers. Sub-subseries: Administration and Services, Officers, Committees, Chapters, School Districts, Schools and Students, Contracts, Elections, Strikes, Conferences, Programs, Publicity, Visitors, Miscellaneous. Schools and Students are arranged by school level (e.g., elementary, high school, etc.), school number and name; School Districts are sorted by district number, and Chapters are arranged by chapter name. Some of the topics and events covered in this subseries include the Ocean Hill-Brownsville strike/crisis, the New York City mass resignations, UFT Spring Conferences, the MES and Dial-A-Teacher programs, and Teacher's Store, as well as pension, chapter, committee, and board meetings.
Subseries I:B: New York State United Teachers (NYSUT). Sub-subseries: Administration and Services, Officers, Committees, Locals and Teacher Associations, Election Districts, Representative Assemblies, School Districts, Schools and Students, Contracts, Conferences, Publicity, Miscellaneous. Schools and Students have been arranged by school level and school name; Locals and Teacher Associations are arranged in alphabetical order by local/association name and by date within local or teacher association name. The largest portion of the subseries is dedicated to photographs of NYSUT locals and teacher associations, which include images documenting strikes, demonstrations, contract negotiations, conferences and community programs.
Subseries I:C: American Federation of Teachers (AFT). Sub-subseries: Conventions, Locals, Miscellaneous. Conventions and Miscellaneous are arranged chronologically; locals are arranged alphabetically by name. Includes AFT national conventions, conferences, and meetings, and images relating to the Professional Staff Congress, the United Federation of College Teachers, and the Nassau Community College Adjunct Faculty Association, as well as a few non-New York AFT locals.
Subseries I:D: Other Teacher Unions. Images relating to teacher unions not directly connected to the UFT, NYSUT or the AFT, including the National Education Association (which was affiliated with NYSUT from 1972-1976), the United University Professions, the Lay Faculty Association, and the Federation of Catholic Teachers, as well as some non-New York teacher unions. Also included are a small number of images relating to New York teacher unions that preceded the UFT, such as the Teachers Guild and NYSUT predecessor, United Teachers of New York.
Subseries I:E: Other Unions. Arranged chronologically. A small number, but diverse range, of images of non-teacher unions, including demonstrations on issues that were supported by the UFT, support demonstrations by other unions for the UFT or NYSUT, and conventions and conferences held by other unions.
Subseries I:F: Other Labor Organizations. These images relate to a number of umbrella or action organizations, including the AFL-CIO, Black Trade Unionists Leadership Council, New York City Central Labor Council, Coalition of Labor Union Women, Frontlash, Italian-American Labor Council, Jewish Labor Committee, and the New York State Public Employees Conference.
Subseries I:G: Other Organizations. Arranged chronologically. A small number of images relating to non-labor-movement organizations, many of them politically progressive, professional, charitable, or fraternal, such as the Consumer Assembly, the Urban League, the United Housing Foundation, the Teacher Education Conference Board, and B'nai B'rith.
Subseries I:H: Non-UFT Strikes. Arranged chronologically. Includes strikes by NYSUT-affiliated organizations (but excludes UFT strikes; the union subseries has a strike sub-subseries of its own), as well as other unions in New York state and throughout the United States.
Subseries I:I: Individuals. The largest single subseries in the collection, it includes portraits of specific individuals, as well as photographs depicting named individuals with other people or in group portraits. While most are of these individuals are UFT or NYSUT officers or members, leaders of other unions or labor organizations (such as George Meany), New York city and state and national politicians (such as President Jimmy Carter), and other prominent figures (such as Martin Luther King, Jr.) are also included.
Subseries I:J: Legislative and Government. Arranged by date. Board of Education meetings, Board of Regents meetings, budget hearings, Taylor Law Hearings, the Rubin Commission, and various other legislative or government hearings.
Subseries I:K: Political. Arranged first by location--New York City, New York State, and Miscellaneous (locations of events are outside of New York or unknown)-and then by date within location. Mainly related to legislative and fiscal issues bearing on education such as tuition tax credits, budget cuts, and the Taylor Law, with many images depicting union political action such as lobbying, Save Our Schools campaigns, VOTE/COPE political action fundraisers, union meetings with legislators and the NYSUT Committee of 100, as well as images that depict national and international political issues not directly related to education, such as Polish Solidarity and Soviet Jewry campaigns.
Subseries I:L: Demonstrations/Rallies/Parades. Arranged first by location--New York City, New York State, and Miscellaneous (place of events are outside of New York or unknown)-and then by date within location. Many photographs show demonstrations outside of school board meetings, City Hall, Gracie Mansion, and individual schools, as well as Labor Day and Solidarity parades. Also encompasses images related to boycotts and jailing of strikers.
Subseries I:M: Schools/Students/Teachers. Divided into two groups: Schools and Students, and Teachers, and arranged by date within each group. Includes photographs of schools and students that have not been identified as belonging to either New York City or State, as well as "generic" images of teachers and classroom scenes.
Subseries I:N: Retired Teachers. Arranged by date. Retired teachers from New York City and New York State.
Subseries I:O: Parents. Arranged by date. Includes a small number of photographs depicting parental involvement in education, such as parent-teacher associations, parent lobbying, and parent participation programs.
Subseries I:P: Special Education. Arranged by date. Includes images relating to education for disabled students, featuring events such as the Special Olympics and the Special Arts Festival.
Subseries I:Q: Training, Certification, and Workshops. Arranged by date. Features images that relate to professional and administrative development programs.
Subseries I:R: Ceremonies. Arranged by date. A diverse range of images documenting various types of ceremonies, including dinners, luncheons, award ceremonies, scholarship presentations, dedications, memorial services, and check presentations.
Subseries I:S: Dedicated Days/Weeks/Celebrations. Arranged by date. Various holiday or dedicated day/week celebrations, shot mostly in schools. Most commonly depicted include Puerto Rican Discovery Day, Black History Week, and Jewish Heritage Week. Also included are images showing a New York City public school observing Earth Day the first year that this day was celebrated.
Subseries I:T: Published New York Teacher Photographs, July 1977-June 1978. Arranged by New York Teacher issue, in chronological order.
Subseries I:U: Miscellaneous. Arranged chronologically.
Series II: United Federation of Teachers General Photograph Files, 1960s-1980s. Consists of miscellaneous images drawn from officers' records and divisions of the union other than its newspaper, the New York Teacher.
Series III: Predecessor Unions, 1928-1961. Arranged chronologically within subseries. Most of the photographs in this series date from the 1940s and 1950s. Many of the images are related to the struggles of the Teachers' Union to defend its members against blacklisting and other manifestations of McCarthy-era repression. Series III is divided into 3 organizational subseries: A: Teachers Union Auxiliary, B: Teachers' Union, C: Teachers' Guild.
Negatives (photographic); Teachers |z New York (State) |z New York.; Teachers' unions.; Schools -- New York (State) -- New York; New York (N.Y.); Black-and-white photographs.; Slides (photographs); American Federation of Teachers; Shanker, Albert.; Selden, David.; Teachers Guild; Feldman, Sandra.; Cogen, Charles, 1903-; Altomare, George.; United Federation of Teachers; Teachers' Union of the City of New York; New York State United Teachers
- Series I: New York Teacher Photograph Files, 1951-1987.
  - Subseries I:A: United Federation of Teachers.
    - Sub-subseries I:A:1: Administration and Services
      - District Pension Meeting, JHS 118 Manhattan, Jan 14, 1963; 767 (Item 767)
      - [UFT?:] Per Session Salary Rates Presentation, Nov 1965; 771 (Item 771)
      - UFT Members on trip to Quito via Equadorian Tours, May 1966; 784 (Item 784)
      - [UFT?:] Inservice Education, Pension Course, Sep 1966; 755 (Item 755)
      - Freedom National Bank, first deposit to ensure added medical benefits for UFT members, Nov 1966 (Item 745)
      - UFT Staff (Spring 1968), proofs and negatives (Item 608)
      - Tax Deferred Annuity meeting, Oct 1969 (Item 910)
      - [UFT?:] Pension Meeting, Oct 3, 1969 (Item 917)
      - UFT Co-Op Housing Site, Staten Island, Jun 1970 (Item 1115)
      - Staten Island Borough Office, Sep 1970 (Item 1152)
      - Queens Borough Office, Sep 21, 1970 (Item 1267)
      - Bronx Borough Office, Sep 21, 1970 (Item 1266)
      - Bronx Borough Office Opening, Sep 25, 1970 (Item 1125)
      - [UFT?:] Payroll Savings Plan, Treasury Department, Sep 30, 1970 (Item 1338)
      - Brooklyn Borough Office Opening, Oct 8, 1970 (Item 1358)
      - Staten Island Borough Office Opening, Oct 16, 1970 (Item 1173)
      - Queens Borough Office Opening, Oct 27, 1970 (Item 1177)
      - [UFT?:] Borough Pension Counselors Meeting, Jan 1971 (Item 1284)
      - [UFT] Pension Fund Meeting, Jan 12, 1971 (Item 1357)
      - Career Training Press Conference, UFT Headquarters, Feb 3, 1971 (Item 1301)
      - [UFT] Pension Fund Meeting, Feb 19, 1971 (Item 1412)
      - UFT Executive Board Meeting, May 10, 1971 (Item 1689)
      - UFT Pension Clinic, Nov 5, 1971 (Item 1731)
      - [UFT] Pension Fund Meeting, Apr 1972 (Item 1357)
      - [UFT?:] JHS Weekend Conference, Apr 28, 1972 (Item 1851)
      - UFT Queens Borough Office, Student Teachers Meeting, May 1972 (Item 2690)